Francisco Hernández

Full-stack Software Engineer

fjch87@gmail.com Portfolio +502 5126-9001 GitHub

Summary

Full-stack software engineer who specializes in building scalable, maintainable and fault resistant applications that create a great user experience using modern and in-demand technologies. I have a huge passion for programming, which I join with my technical knowledge to focus on delivering great software products. My repertoire includes programming languages and tools such as Python, JavaScript, TypeScript, ReactJS, Ionic, MUI, Node.js, Express.js, MongoDB, and more

Relevant experience

Software engineer @ Simera (Project ExaCare)

Jun 2023 - Present // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Worked on the development of a customer facing web application using TypeScript, React.js, MUI and React Query
- Built E2E tests using Playwright to test React.js application's flows
- Built endpoints in REST API and implemented new features to extend back-end functionality in project based in microservices architecture using TypeScript, Sequelize and the Serverless Framework
- Built unit tests and integration tests using Jest to ensure the correctness of new codebase added to extend back-end functionality
- Built migrations in Sequelize to change PostgreSQL DB tables and updated models when extending back-end project functionalities

Skills: TypeScript React.js MUI PostgreSQL Sequelize Serverless Framework Playwright Jest React Query

Software engineer @ Cognits (Project ShareGRO)

Sep 2021 - Feb 2023 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Worked on the development of customer facing and administrator web applications using HTML, CSS/SASS, TypeScript (React.js) and the Ionic framework
- Implemented GraphQL API in Node.js project using Express.js and express-graphql to serve queries and mutations for React.js applications connected using Apollo Client
- Built endpoints in GraphQL API and implemented new features to extend back-end functionality in Python based project using Graphene-Python library and the Starlette framework
- Implemented third party integrations for several services like SMS verification with Twilio, email sending with SendGrid, broker dealer services and financial services in Node.js and Python based projects

Skills: TypeScript React.js Ionic CSS/SASS Python Graphene-Python Express.js MongoDE PostgreSQL Storybook

Software engineer @ Cognits (Project Onramp Invest)

Jul 2021 - Sep 2021 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Gave support and developed new features to extend user experience functionality in existing front-end projects using JavaScript, Vue.js and CSS
- ▶ Built new endpoints in existing REST API for data manipulation using FastAPI in Python based project

Skills: JavaScript Node.js Vue.js Python FastAPI REST API

Software engineer @ Cognits (Project RLI Corp)

Mar 2021 - Sep 2021 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Created necessary stylesheets using CSS/Sass to replicate quotation's web system for insurance company using the corresponding brand guidelines coming from Figma designs
- Developed all the required API integrations in quotation's web system by following the given Swagger REST API documentation using Mendix technology

Skills: Java CSS/SASS Mendix Swagger Figma

Software Engineer and Teaching assistant @ Galileo University

Jan 2019 - Nov 2022 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Developed a college level web system using JavaScript libraries and frameworks which is and has been used in several Computer Science courses by hundreds of users for the administration of class assignments and to provide the students the best possible learning experience
- Supported students in laboratories building algorithms when teaching them important basic concepts using programming languages

Languages

Spanish English

Main skills

Programming Languages

JavaScript (ES6), TypeScript, HTML, CSS/Sass, GraphQL, Python

Libraries & Frameworks

React.js, Vue.js, Ionic, Storybook, Apollo Client, Bootstrap, MUI, Semantic UI, jQuery, Node.js, Express.js, Next.js, FastAPI, Graphene-Python, Mendix

Tools & Platforms

Git, Heroku, Docker, GCP (Google Compute Engine, Google Storage), AWS (EC2, ECS, ECR, S3, CloudFront), GitHub actions/pages

Design

Figma, InVision

Education

Galileo University

2017 - 2020 // Guatemala, Guatemala Bachelor of Science in Engineering in Systems, Informatics and Computer Science

Galileo University

2021 - 2022 // Guatemala, Guatemala Master's degree in operations research

Projects

Computer Science Educative Web Platform

Web app built with Node.js, EJS, Bootstrap, Express and MongoDB to manage different assignments, announcements and to provide interactive material for learning programming languages to 6 different classrooms with over 25 students each

Interests

Basketball, play the guitar, play videogames, watch TV shows